<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-12-15T05:22:37+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Tropical climate variability Germany visit</title><link href="/blog/2025/SPP2299/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tropical climate variability Germany visit"/><published>2025-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2025/SPP2299</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2025/SPP2299/"><![CDATA[<img-comparison-slider> <figure slot="first"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/german_Autumn.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/german_Autumn.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figure slot="second"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/german_Autumn_noir.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/german_Autumn_noir.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </img-comparison-slider> <h1 id="science-and-autumn-in-germany">Science and autumn in Germany</h1> <p>After many years, it was so nice to be back in Germany the first time again during Autumn. I forgot how beautiful and golden this season presents in Germany with the smell of freshly fallen leaves everywhere. Many childhood memories running through mountains of leaves and collecting chestnuts for the animals. Golden leaves, crips mornings and admittedly I could have skipped the time to wait for the low lying “graune Suppe” of clouds to disappear during the course of the day. But even those grey days add the cosy feeling you only get during German autumn.</p> <p>My trip started in Bremen for the SPP2299 meeting—a DFG priority program on tropical climate variability and coral reefs. The meeting was held near a fantastic science museum called Universum Bremen. I was impressed by the hands-on experiments and the tight involvement and collaboration with German universities and research institutions which brings this science museum very close to cutting edge of research.</p> <h1 id="spp2299-highlights">SPP2299 Highlights</h1> <p>The SPP meeting in Bremen on tropical climate variability and coral reefs was incredible and packed with interesting people and talks. I can’t possibly easily summarise the incredible amount of research done in this area. But a few things stuck with me, and I am excited to so many things coming out soon. An example is how coral records can exaggerate past decadal variability compared to gridded SST datasets (Dolman &amp; Laepple, 2025 [Dolman, A. M., &amp; Laepple, T. (2025). Temperature variability on coral reefs versus Gridded SST – The long and the short of it. Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems, 26, e2025GC012351. ]). The paper suggests that coral records reflect very localised temperature fluctuations, while gridded SST products provide a larger, averaged view of the ocean. The difference in variability is mainly attributed to this difference in spatial scale, rather than other potential influences on the temperature data. The study used in-situ temperature loggers on coral reefs to help isolate the effects of spatial scale from other non-climatic factors that can influence coral temperature reading. Another highlight was work on volcanic cooling and freshening in the Indian Ocean during the early 19th century by Hana Camelia Marum. Looking forward seeing this out.</p> <swiper-container keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Flug.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Flug.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Fruehstueck.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Fruehstueck.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Ummenhofer,Freund.JPG" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Ummenhofer,Freund.JPG" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <p>After Bremen, I took the train to Hamburg for research visits at MPI and DKRZ. Traveling by train felt like a novelty after years in Australia. It’s such a nice way of traveling even though delays are part of the game, certainly for the Deutsche Bahn…</p> <p>Hamburg is a beautiful city and somewhat a hot spot for climate related research. With the Max Planck Institute of Meteorology and the Deutschen Klima Rechenzentrum certainly leading role in German and international research. I had great discussions focused on how we can utilise artificial intelligence in atmospheric science. While challenging, it seems to offer short cuts which usually require immense resources. For example, we are often interested to quantify the range of natural or intrinsic climate variability. How much does rainfall vary over the years? Some years are really wet, some very dry but most often we see average rainfall. Often the observational records isn’t enough, a very dry year could be a very rare event that hasn’t been observed in our odd 80 years of reliable observations. Climate science often borrows climate simulations for those kinds of questions. Running a climate model once, gives you one realisation similar to our one and only Earth. But there are multiple pathways of alternative Earths possible which can provide us with a number of different possible realities that certain things in our climate system vary. Running climate simulations run over and over again with slightly different initial conditions can provide you with a range of variability but annoyingly it is computational very expensive. AI can help there creating large ensembles of climate simulations reasonable cheap as shown by Meuer et al 2025. (Latent Ensemble Generator (LatEnGen) -&gt; Meuer, Johannes, et al. “Latent Diffusion and Spatio-Temporal Transformers Generate Large Ensemble Climate Simulations.” IEEE Transactions on Artificial Intelligence (2025).</p> <swiper-container keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/GraueSuppe.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/GraueSuppe.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Pforte.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Pforte.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Hamburg.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Hamburg.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <p>Other great applications include the reconstructions of data sparse observational fields. Instrumental records only cover a fraction of Earth’s history—less than 30% of the surface had measurements before 1900. AI-based reconstructions have shown to be able to reconstruct these fields more accurately and can even help resolve uncertainties in for example early 19th century sea surface temperature trends (Addressing early 20th-century cold bias in ocean surface temperature observations (Sippel et al., 2024). Cutting edge AI can even be applied to past climate extremes like warm and cold days and nights (Plésiat et al., 2024) which is usually very hard. Observed extremes often suffer from spatial gaps and inaccuracies due to inadequate spatial extrapolation. AI can reconstruct past climate extremes of (warm and cold days and nights) and more e.g. TX90p and gridded extreme indices. Plésiat, É., Dunn, R.J.H., Donat, M.G. et al. Artificial intelligence reveals past climate extremes by reconstructing historical records. Nat Commun 15, 9191 (2024). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-53464-2. These AI techniques can even help to discover past volcanic eruptions. Linking specific events e.g. past volcanic eruptions with its origin via AI -&gt; Meuer, Johannes &amp; Timmreck, Claudia &amp; Fang, Shih-Wei &amp; Kadow, Christopher. (2024). Fingerprints of past volcanic eruptions can be detected in historical climate records using machine learning. Communications Earth &amp; Environment. 5. 10.1038/s43247-024-01617-y.</p> <p>Overall, this ties well in with ongoing work on ENSO diversity and transitions, where understanding how events evolve and shift between states is key for improving predictions. Using Markov chain approaches (Freund et al., 2024) highlight how ENSO behaviour has changed over time and how models project future transitions. Combining these statistical frameworks with AI-driven reconstructions could open new doors for exploring ENSO complexity in both past and future climates. Instrumental data, especially in the tropical Pacific, are imperfect and often insufficient for studying pre-industrial ENSO. Future work utilising these AI advances could shed new light on long-term warming patterns and diverse ENSO events using AI-driven reconstructions. So there is plenty of scope for collaboration on topics like AI-based climate science, reconstructions. For now, it’s back home with lots of ideas and a renewed appreciation for how science, Germany, and a few golden leaves can make for a memorable journey.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Laub.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Laub.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Beautiful Autumn. </div> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The sequence of ENSO events from one year to the next]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ENSO transitions - a game of domino</title><link href="/blog/2024/Domino/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ENSO transitions - a game of domino"/><published>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/Domino</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/Domino/"><![CDATA[<div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Domino_tiles_ENSO_Transitions.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Domino_tiles_ENSO_Transitions.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> </div> <hr/> <p>You can think about past ENSO events as a game of domino. The chain of dominoes symbolises the sequence of ENSO events which gradually increases in length each year. While some tiles are blank representing neutral conditions or a “joker”, other tiles show El Niño and La Niña conditions. To play by the rules, only matching ends must touch each other.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <audio src="/assets/audio/Freund%20et%20al%202024%20summary.wav" controls=""/> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Listen to a podcast on ENSO transitions (NotebookLM) </div> <p>When we looked at the sequence of ENSO events or domino tiles during the observed period, we first did an inventory of tiles. We found some expected observations like tiles expressing a high likelihood of an La Niña event to follow an El Niño event. This tile, or transition as we call it, is one of the most common tiles in the games. But what we also found was that some tiles are missing or simply don’t exist.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Annual_workshop_CLEX_W21C_Poster.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Annual_workshop_CLEX_W21C_Poster.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Poster for the annual workshop of CLEX/W21C. </div> <hr/>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The sequence of ENSO events from one year to the next]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">La Niña possible, but not very likely</title><link href="/blog/2024/Test/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="La Niña possible, but not very likely"/><published>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2024/Test</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2024/Test/"><![CDATA[<p>Climatologists, farmers, and other essential decision-makers are holding their breath as the potential development of a La Niña event hangs in the balance. The development of an La Niña event is on the caps to be decided.</p> <p>For Australia, La Niña is often associated with increased rainfall, which can significantly impact agriculture and water resources. The uncertainty surrounding this event means that planning ahead becomes both essential and challenging.</p> <p>Recently, the Bureau of Meteorology, keeping a close eye on the latest observations and modelling results, has raised its ENSO outlook to a La Niña watch, indicating a 50% chance that La Niña could develop in the coming months.</p> <p>However, many are wondering why this La Niña signal is emerging so late. Typically, signs of ENSO events are observed earlier in the year, giving scientists and decision-makers more time to prepare for the associated impacts.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Designer_LaNina.jpeg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Designer_LaNina.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/7.jpg" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/7.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A simple, elegant caption looks good between image rows, after each row, or doesn't have to be there at all. </div> <hr/> <h2 id="la-nina-could-be-declared-this-summer">La Nina could be declared this summer</h2> <p>ENSO events have a well-documented history of triggering devastating global natural disasters. The 2015-16 El Niño, for example, affected nearly 60 million people across Africa, Latin America, the Caribbean, and the Asia-Pacific, leading to widespread droughts, floods, food insecurity, disease outbreaks, malnutrition, and respiratory issues.</p> <p>Following the rare “triple-dip” La Niña from 2020-2023, Australia is bracing for the potential impacts of yet another La Niña event. The looming threat brings concerns of heavy rainfall and heightened flooding risks across the country.</p> <p>Should La Niña be declared in 2024, it would mark the fourth ENSO event in just five years—an unusually active period for ENSO, though not without historical precedent. As Australia watches closely, the possible arrival of La Niña adds urgency to preparing for what could be another season of extreme weather.</p> <hr/> <img-comparison-slider> <figure slot="first"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/sst-monthly_gamssa.anom.global.20230901.hr.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/sst-monthly_gamssa.anom.global.20230901.hr.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figure slot="second"> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/sst-monthly_gamssa.anom.global.20240901.hr.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/sst-monthly_gamssa.anom.global.20240901.hr.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </img-comparison-slider> <p>Example of September sea surface temperatures of 2023 versus 2024 based on the Bureau of Meteorologie http://www.bom.gov.au/</p> <hr/> <h2 id="late-prediction-of-enso-events--harder-to-predict">Late prediction of ENSO events- harder to predict?</h2> <p>Predicting ENSO events like El Niño and La Niña has always been tricky. These events follow the seasonal cycle, usually developing in autumn, peaking in late spring or summer, and weakening by the next autumn. However, predictions are hardest during the Southern Hemisphere’s autumn, a period known as the ‘predictability barrier,’ when forecasting accuracy drops significantly.</p> <p>This year, we’ve reached late spring without a clear declaration of La Niña. Why the delay?</p> <p>The Bureau of Meteorology points to climate change as a factor. Oceans have absorbed much of the excess heat from global warming, and warmer waters are being observed globally. This makes it harder to spot the specific warming patterns linked to La Niña, which usually causes wetter conditions in Australia.</p> <p>The complexity of the ocean-atmosphere system adds to the difficulty. Even with improved prediction models, understanding ENSO still requires better data on deep ocean processes and how winds affect the system. Global warming may also be changing how often and how intensely these events occur.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="more-precise-and-earlier-el-niño-southern-oscillation-forecasts">More precise and earlier El Niño Southern Oscillation forecasts</h2> <p>A new study published in Environmental Research Letters has assessed the likelihood of different types of ENSO events—either in the Eastern or Central Pacific—occurring in succession. The results could lead to more accurate, long-range forecasts, giving communities additional time to plan and prepare.</p> <p>By analysing weather observational records over the past 150 years and climate models, the research team was able to quantify the likelihood of ENSO events occurring in two consecutive years and examined the sequence of past El Niño and La Niña events of different types and identified clear patterns.</p> <p>The study found that most El Niño events are followed by neutral conditions the next year, with a likelihood of 37–55.6%. However, La Niña behaves differently. There’s a 40% chance that a Central Pacific El Niño could follow an Eastern Pacific La Niña, and a 27.8% chance of two consecutive Central Pacific La Niña events.</p> <p>“Australia recently experienced a strong Eastern Pacific El Niño starting in September 2023,” said Dr. Freund. “Our findings suggest only a 16.7% chance of La Niña developing in 2024, and if it does, it will likely peak in the Central Pacific.”</p> <p>As climate change accelerates, the frequency, types, and transitions of ENSO events are expected to shift, with fewer calm, neutral years between events. The study indicates a greater likelihood of Central Pacific La Niña events following Eastern Pacific El Niño events, which may play out in the coming season.</p> <p>Importantly, these results allow for more advanced ENSO predictions. Based on current conditions, the odds of an ENSO event can now be given up to a year in advance, providing valuable information to guide decisions. This helps identify not only what is likely but also what is unlikely to happen.</p> <p>For the upcoming season, if La Niña does emerge, it is expected to be weak and short-lived.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After a strong eastern Pacific El Niño will we have a La Niña developing in 2024]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Unraveling the history of El Niño flavours</title><link href="/blog/2019/Natgeo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unraveling the history of El Niño flavours"/><published>2019-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/2019/Natgeo</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/Natgeo/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="coral-records-from-the-tropical-oceans-reveal-the-first-400-year-long-seasonal-record-of-different-el-niño-events-this-record-shows-an-astonishing-change-of-el-niños-flavour-in-the-most-recent-decades">Coral records from the tropical oceans reveal the first 400 year-long seasonal record of different El Niño events. This record shows an astonishing change of El Niño’s flavour in the most recent decades.</h2> <p>El Niño events can have many different characteristics and influence the lives of millions of people around the world. Over the past decades, considerable effort has been invested to study and describe El Niño events. However, how El Niño will behave with future climate change remains an open question. El Niño events already pose several challenges. At first, El Niño events are rather rare, happening approximately every 2-7 years. Only a handful of events have been directly observed since the advent of high-quality satellite imagery. A further complication is the fact that no two El Niño events are alike. Neither the initial conditions in ocean and atmosphere nor the impacts on temperature and rainfall, ecosystems, societies and economies are the same; they differ substantially. The complexity around those El Niño events has been slightly simplified with the recognition of different flavours of El Niño. Depending on where exactly the strongest sea surface warming in the tropical Pacific Ocean occurs, El Niño events can be distinguished into Central and Eastern Pacific type events. Still, the limited number of observed El Niño remains an issue.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/Images_blog/Fig_Schematic_together_only.png" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/Images_blog/Fig_Schematic_together_only.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> A simple, elegant caption looks good between image rows, after each row, or doesn't have to be there at all. </div> <hr/> <p>By looking back, we can extend our record of El Niño events. This can better equip us understand current and future changes. Records from coral reefs are not only long enough to provide information about past ocean conditions, but also detailed enough to tell us about seasonal changes in the tropical Pacific. However, using coral records at seasonal scales is rarely attempted.</p> <h2 id="focus-on-seasonal-differences-instead-of-annual-averages">Focus on seasonal differences instead of annual averages</h2> <p>Scientists have previously used corals as silent archives of past ocean conditions. The hard skeleton of corals is built out of carbonates containing multiple elements including oxygen isotopes. Living corals incorporate these elements into their skeleton each time they grow, storing the chemical properties of the surrounding water at that time. During the course of a coral lifetime, the conditions that existed in its surrounding waters remain stored in their skeleton hidden in their growth bands. By measuring the chemical composition of these growth bands, scientists are able to retrieve the conditions that influenced its past growth. This can include information about rainfall, temperature or how salty the surrounding water used to be. Compared to trees which build similar growth rings each year, corals grow at a faster rate and can record oceanic condition at a much finer time resolution, ranging from biweekly to seasonal. These seasonal coral records have been collected from around the tropical Pacific by scientists across the world, involving decades of research, field trips and lab work. Our work has been made possible thanks to these efforts. By combining this network of corals records, we have been able to dig deeper into the common seasonal information stored in the corals and identify past El Niño events.</p> <p>Prepared with an idea and preliminary results focusing on seasonal differences instead of annual averages, I presented this work to international experts. It was after this that Australian’s leading experts of past corals, Assoc Prof Nerilie Abram and Assoc Prof Helen McGregor, joint the team. Together with climate scientists, Dr Ben Henley, Prof David Karoly, and Dr Dietmar Dommenget, we worked out a way to identify and distinguish the different flavours of El Niño.</p> <p>We found that a machine learning algorithm was the best tool for identifying the different flavours of El Niño. These days big data and machine learning algorithms are helping us in our everyday life. They are behind the next Netflix movie, advertisement or the automatic detection of holiday photos. Although used all around us, (earth) scientists are still hesitant to apply these algorithms to their data of the physical world.</p> <p>In our study, a supervised machine learning algorithm has been applied to help to identify the different types of El Niño and importantly distinguished them from each other. Similar to a regression approach often used in sciences, a model is fitted to describe a process based on some known information. In our case, we can use observed sea surface temperatures in the tropical Pacific and know which years have been El Niño events in the central Pacific versus those in the eastern Pacific. Since 1950, we have observed eight Central Pacific El Niño events and eight Eastern Pacific El Niño events, but what do have all those events have in common? And more importantly, what distinguishes them from each other? Supervised machine learning can help us answer these questions.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="innovative-big-data--machine-learning-techniques">Innovative big data &amp; machine learning techniques</h2> <p>A supervised machine learning algorithm known as a decision tree, can find the underlying rules which lead to El Niño events. Similar to flowcharts or quizzes, like “what kind of Avenger are you?”, a decision tree finds consecutive paths which lead to a particular outcome. For example, your decision about the t-shirt colour, followed by our choice of superpower, may result in being more Captain Marvel than the Hulk. In our case, the decision tree describes pathways about sea surface temperatures in different seasons, resulting in either Central Pacific El Niño events, Eastern Pacific El Niño events or no El Niño. This novel method has the advantage of being able to identify and classify El Niño events very precisely. If the temperatures in the Pacific warm up during the summer and peak during Christmas time, we can detect an El Niño based on its seasonal evolution and where the warming started.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="first-seasonal-record-of-el-niño-activity">First seasonal record of El Niño activity</h2> <p>The first seasonal record of El Niño activity and our classification approach allowed us now to identify the El Niño events of the past 400 years. For the first time, with this extended information from the coral records, we can put recent changes of El Niños into a long-term context. Over the past 400 years, both the Eastern and Central Pacific El Niño events have occurred roughly at the same rate. By the end of the 20th century more El Niño tends to occur in the Central Pacific rather than the East. Additionally, fewer but more intense El Niño events happened in the Eastern Pacific.</p> <p>Our results highlight the importance of long-term paleoclimate timeframes to assess and compare recent and future changes. The instrumental record is simply not long enough and El Niño events are too rare to fully understand the natural behaviour of El Niño.</p> <p>This study could shed new light on the tropical Pacific and its decadal to multidecadal variations, as well as providing a new baseline to constrain and study El Niño events using climate models. An accurate simulation of both flavours of El Niño is a necessary step for climate scientist to understand the recently high abundance of Central Pacific El Niño events. Only with this understanding can we confidently predict future behavior of El Niño in a changing climate.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After a strong eastern Pacific El Niño will we have a La Niña developing in 2024]]></summary></entry></feed>